<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke of Barthram priest intreatinge of the bodye and bloude of Christ wryten to greate Charles the Emperoure, and set forth. vii.C. yeares a goo. and imprinted. an. d[omi]ni M.D.XLviii. Cum preuilegio, ad imprimendum solum.</title>
            <title>De corpore et sanguine Domini. English</title>
            <author>Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850871</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10468)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke of Barthram priest intreatinge of the bodye and bloude of Christ wryten to greate Charles the Emperoure, and set forth. vii.C. yeares a goo. and imprinted. an. d[omi]ni M.D.XLviii. Cum preuilegio, ad imprimendum solum.</title>
                  <title>De corpore et sanguine Domini. English</title>
                  <author>Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.</author>
                  <author>Trithemius, Johannes, 1462-1516.</author>
                  <author>Hugh, William, d. 1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Andrewes paryshe in the waredropt by Thomas Raynalde, and Anthony Kyngstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Barthram priest = Ratramnus.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by William Hugh, of: De corpore et sanguine Domini.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴ (-C4).</note>
                  <note>Includes "The lyfe of Barthram priest" by Johannes Thrithemius on title page verso.</note>
                  <note>In this edition title has "intreatinge .. bloude .. Christ". Quire C is from the same setting as STC 20748.5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16106:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The boke of Barthram Prieſt intreatinge of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt wryten to greate Charles the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure / and ſet forth. vii. C. years a goo.</head>
            <p>And Imprinted An. dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i M.D.XLviii.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum Preuilegio, ad Imprimendum Solum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical_introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:16106:2"/>
            <head>¶ The lyfe of Barthram prieſt</head>
            <byline>by Iohannes Thrithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us.</byline>
            <p>BArthram prieſt and monke, very well learned in ſeculer diſciplyns and in holye ſcryptures, ſubtyle of wytte, eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and no leſſe notable for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> integretie of the lyfe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his learning wrote many bokes, wherof I haue ſene but a fewe. He wrote a commendable worke touchinge predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Kynge Charles brother of Lothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, and a boke concernynge the body and bloude of the lorde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He floryſhed in the tyme of Lotherius Emperoure an. dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Xlviii.</p>
            <p>¶ A man ſhall not perceyue the mynde of the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tor excepte he rede the boke throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and conferre the fyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> art wyth the latter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16106:2"/>
            <head>¶ The preface to Charles the Emperoure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me (moſte famous Prynce) to ſignifye vnto your mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifycence, what opinion I haue tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hynge the myſterye of the body and bloude of Chryſte Truelye as it is a commaundement, not vnworthye of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oure regall and pryncelye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtate ſo thexecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, to the peruite of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth ſhalbe verye dyfficile and hard. For what is more worthye of your regall prouidenc, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be catholy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke wyſe, touchynge the holye myſteryes of the bodye and blod of chriſt, whych hath auanced you, to your regal ſeat And further not to permyt your ſubiects, dyuerſly to thynke of the bodye and bloude of chryſt wherin doutles, the ſome of chryſtyan redemptyon doth conſyſt Truly no ſmall contrauerſye is ſprong for aſmuche as ſome ſaye that the ſacramente of the body and bloud newlye celebrate in the church is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no Fygur: obuelacion or couer, And agayne, that other ſome doth ſaye theſe thynges to be contayned vnder a fygure of a myſterye, &amp; that it is one thynge which appereth to our corporal ſences: &amp; another that is ſene wyth the eye of oure fayth. And not wythſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge that thappoſtle wrytyng to the fathfull word haue al men to fauour one thyng, ſaye one, one thing and that no ſcyſme ſhuld appere among them. Yet they be wonderfully deuyded in dede, thynkynge dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly of the body &amp; blode of chryſt. Wherfore youre regall hyghnes, prouoked wyth the zeale of faythe, &amp; not well pleaſed W<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thynges (coueryug alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the apoſtles precepte, that al men ſhulde thynke and ſay one thynge) ſearcheth diligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lye for the ſecrete of the truthe. Wherby it maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16106:3"/>that haue wandred oute of the way, into the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Wher vpon you diſdayne not, to aſke the truthe of thys matrer, euen of very poore men, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge that the myſterye of ſuche a ſecrete, can not be knowen, but by the reuela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of god. Whyche ſheweth the lyghte of hys truthe: by whome ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe hym to electe. Uerelye as it is pleaſaunce for me poore man to obey your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, ſo it is hard to diſpute vpon a matter, beyng far beyonde the ſences of men, &amp; that cannot be knowen. But by the erudition of the holye gooſt. Therfore I at thys tyme beynge at youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements: throughe hys grace of whome we wyll ſpeake, ſhall declare accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to my habilite, what I do thynke, concernynge this ſacrament, not leanyng to myne o wne wyll, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> perſuynge the fote ſteppes of the olde fathers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>¶ The boke of Barthram prfeſte touthynge the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and bloude of Thriſt wryten to greate Charles the Emperoure.</head>
            <p>YOure hyghnes deſyrethe to knowe whether that the body and bloude of chriſte whyche is receyued in the churche by the mouthes of the faythfull, be in myſtery or in verite. &amp;c. That is to ſaye, whether it conteyneth ſome ſecrete thynge that is only euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the eyes of fayth, or wythoute the veale of any myſterye that thynge is loked vpon of the externe ſyght of the bodye, whych the inwarde eye of the mynde doth beholde. So that whatſoeuer is done, apereth manifeſtely or no &amp;c, And whether it be that body whych was born of Mary, that ſuffred dyed, was buryed roſe agayne, aſcended into heauen, and ſytteth on the ryght hande of the father or no &amp;c. Of theſe two queſtions, let vs begyn wyth the fyrſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leſt we be letted with doutfulnes, &amp; ambyguyte.</p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:16106:3"/>
               <p>Defyne we what a fygure is, and what the verite is that we may certaynly knowe how, &amp; whyche waye, we ought to reaſon A fygure is a certayn obumbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, or ſhadoyng, declaryng the thynge whiche he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth by ſome veales or couers. As for an example, we meaninge the worde, do name breade. As in the lordes prayer, we deſyre our daylye breade to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Or whan Chriſte ſayeth in the goſpell. I am the lyuely breade, whych haue diſcended from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Or whan he calleth hym ſelfe a vyne, and hys apoſtles braunches, ſayeng: I am the true vyne, you verely the braunches. In all theſe one thynge is ſpoken, and an other thyng vnderſtande. The veryte truly is a demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of a manifeſt thynge, couered wyth no Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of ſhadowes, but inſinuate, wyth pure playne and naturall ſignificatyons. As wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſaye, that chriſte was borne of a virgyn that he ſuffered, that he was crucifyed, dead, &amp; buryed. Here is nothynge ſhadowed wyth fygures, but the veritie of the thynges, ſhewed by naturall ſignificacions of wordes. Neyther muſte we vnderſtande, any other thyng here, then that why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is expreſſed. But not ſo in thoſe thynges that we ſpake of before. For ſubſtauncyally, neyther is the bread chriſte, neyther the wyne is chriſte, neyther yet are the braunches the apoſtles, wherfore in thoſe is a fygure, in the other the verite is ſhewed in narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. That is to ſay. A naked and playne ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now let vs retourne to thoſe thinges for whoſe cauſe they be ſpoken. That is the bodye and blode of chriſte. Truelye yf the myſterye be done vnder no fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, then do we nought in callynge it a myſterye, for that can not haue the name of a myſterie, wherin no thynge is hydde, where nothynge is remoued frome our corporall ſences, where nothing is, couered wyth any veale: but that bread whyche by the myſterye of the
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16106:4"/>kynde of the creature and the ſhape of vyſyble thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the breade and the wyne haue nothynge chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in them, and yf they haue nothynge chaunged in them, they be none other then they ware before.</p>
               <p>YOure hyghnes (noble prynce) perceyueth to what paſſe the intellectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thes thynges do come. Whych be of a contrarye iudgemente, they deny, whych they are thought to affyrme And they are prouyde to diſtroye that they do beleue. For they faythfullye confeſſe the bodye and bloude of Chriſt, and in ſo doynge doutles they proteſt that the bread and wyne be not the ſame they ware. &amp; her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore yf they be not the ſame, they ware before, they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue receyuyd mutation, Seynge that thys can not be denyed, let them declare how they be chaunged. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye corporallye a man ſhall peceyue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hynge to be chaunged, therfore they muſt confeſſe that the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion is made other wyſe then corporallye, &amp; alſo that not to be the thyng which is ſene in verite, but ſome other whyche is not perceyued to be thoughe hys power and peculyer benynge, or yf they wyll not con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe thys: nedes they muſt denye the body and bloud of chriſt, whych is a wycked thyng to do, not in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des only but alſo in thought: but foraſmuch as they do confeſſe the body and bloude of chriſte to be there and that it cannot be there but by the reaſon of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion frome a worſe thynge to a better it muſte fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that the mutacion be made not corporallye, but ſpirituallye, yet and ſo that we maye ſaye that it is do ſpiritually. For vnder the veale of corporall bread and wyne, is the ſpirituall bodye and bloud of chriſt yet is there not the exiſtencie of too dyuers thynges, that is to ſaye: of the bodye and the ſpyrite, but one, and the ſame thynge after one ſorte, is the kynde of
<pb facs="tcp:16106:4"/>breade and wyne, &amp; after one other ſorte the body and bloude of chriſt for in that both of them are touched: they be the kyndes of corporall creatures, &amp; through the power by the which they at ſpiritually made they be the myſteries of the body and bloud of Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Let vs conſyder the well of holy baptyſme, whych is called not wythout a cauſe the well of lyfe, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that is confyrmeth thos that diſcende into it wyth the mounte of a better lyfe, &amp; maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyue to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce whych ware before dead in ſynne, The element of the water hath not hys power, for yf it ſhuld not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the vertue of ſainctificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it could not waſſhe away the ſpotte of ſynne. And yf it ſholde not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the vygore of lyfe vtterlye, it ſholde not be able to gyue lyfe to the deade. I meane not my fleſſhe but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſoule, yet in the fountayne yf we haue reſpect onelye to the thynge whych our corporall ſence comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, we ſhall fynde nothynge but water ſubiecte to corruption, and that whych hath none other vertue, but to waſſhe our bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es Yt after that the vertue of the holy gooſt hath acceſſe by the concrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on of the baptyſer, yt is of the efficacy, not only to waſſhe oure bodyes, but alſo by a ſpirituall power to waſſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the ſpiritual fylthe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſolles. Lo in one ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment we ſe two thynges, the one reſyſtinge: the other that is to ſaye, a corruptyble thing to gyue in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a thynge wythout lyfe to contrybute lyfe. Therfore knowe that in thys well is one thyng ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyble and therfore mutable and curruptible. Alſo an other thynge that onely fayth beholdeth, and therfore incorruptible &amp; immortall. And yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requyre what that is whych waſſheth the body it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s nothynge but an eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but yf a man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder that whych inwarde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly purgeth, that is a lyuely vertue a vertue of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication a vertue of immortalyte, therfore the lycore
<pb facs="tcp:16106:5"/>in hys propertie is corruptible in the myſterye, &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vertue, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the bodye &amp; the bloude of chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered outwardely is a creature doughtles ſubiecte to mutabilite &amp; corrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pondre the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the myſterye, it is lyfe geuynge immortalite to thos that be partakers of it. Therfore it is not al one thynge that is ſene &amp; that is beleued. For thos thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be ſene do onely fede the corruptyble bodye, they beynge corruptible them ſelues. But thos thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whych are not ſene, do fede the immortall ſolles, they beynge immortall them ſelues. The apoſtel wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge to the Corinthians, ſayeth: know you not that all oure fathers ware vnder a cloude, that all paſſed ouer the ſee, that all they were baptyſed in Moyſes in the cloude &amp; in the ſee, that all they haue eaten the ſame ſprituall meate, and that all they haue dronken the ſame ſpiritual drinke? They dyd drinke of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall ſtone folowing them, the ſtone alſo was chriſt Thus we perceyue that the ſee had a kynde of baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, &amp; the clowde alſo that the fathers of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ware baptized in the cloude &amp; in the ſee. Coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the cloude or the ſee of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues haue the vertue of baptiſme, or coulde they ſanctifye the people. Yet dare we not accuſe the Apoſtell of lyenge, for that he ſayd our fathers ware baptyz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in the cloud &amp; in the ſee. And although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyſme was a type &amp; a fygure of the baptyſme of chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now vſed in the church Yet no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath hys wytnes wyl ſay, that it alſo was not baptyſme it ſelfe, or that oure fathers ware not baptyzed therin, except he wyll varye frome the Apoſtell as a mad ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore the ſee &amp; clowde, not in that they ware creatures &amp; bodyes deade, toke the clerenes of ſanctifycatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſperyte. For in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a viſyble forme whych appereth playnlye to the corporall ſence, and wythin a ſpirituall power which was onely euydent to the eyes of the mynde &amp; fayth.
<pb facs="tcp:16106:5"/>Lykewyſe manna geuen to the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the water flowinge out of the rocke ware corporall and corporally they fedde the people &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drinke, Yt the Apoſtel nameth that manna &amp; that water ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meat, &amp; ſpiritual drinke. and why verely bycauſe that there was in thos corporall ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces a ſpiritual power of the worde, whych fedde the myndes, rather then the bodyes of the beleuynge people &amp; ſpiritually gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drinke, &amp; not wythſtanding theyr meate and drynke dyd prefygurate the bodye &amp; bloude of chriſte whych the church doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>rate. Yet ſaynt Paule affyrmeth that oure fathers dyd eate the ſame ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all meate, and drinke the ſame ſpiritual drinke.</p>
               <p>A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll aſke perauenture what he meaneth by this worde (the ſame) truly he meaneth that they dyd eate the ſame ſpirituall meate whyche the faythfull eateth &amp; drinketh now a dayes in the church, we may not vnderſtande dyuers thynges, for chriſte is &amp; was alwayes on. And the ſame chriſt whych fedde the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple that ware the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptyzed in the deſerte, in the clow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, &amp; in the ſee wyth hys fleſſhe and his bloude, fedeth now the people in the church of hys faythful with the breade of hys bodye, &amp; the water of hys bloude, thys thynge the Apoſtel dyd playnly declare by that which foloweth, ſayenge: they haue eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ſpirituall meate &amp; dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ſpirituall drinke They dyd drinke of the ſame ſpirituall ſtone followyng them &amp; the ſtone was chriſte So we vnderſtande that chriſt was in the ſpirituall ſtone in the deſerte. And that he gaue the water of hys bloude to the people And afterwarde gaue to vs hys bodye whyche was borne of a virgyn &amp; crucifyed for the helthe of the faythfull. And not only that we myght be redemyd: but alſo that we myght drynke therof. It is a maruelous thynge: that Chriſt all though he was incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſyble &amp; ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:16106:6"/>And that he had not yt put vpon hym the nature of man, had not yet taſted death for the helthe of the worlde, nor redemyd vs wyth hys bloud. For al that our fathers in the deſerte by a ſpiritual meate &amp; an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſyble drinke, dyd eate hys body &amp; drynke hys blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. As the apoſtell wytneſſeth, ſayeng: our fathers ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue eaten the ſame ſpirituall meate, &amp; dronken the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſpirituall drinke, here we cannot know by reaſon how this thinge was done. Yet to the doynges fayth muſt be adhibited for it is he truly whych by hys om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotente vertue turneth the breade &amp; the wyne ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually into hys fleſſhe &amp; hys bloude, &amp; alſo whyche at the tyme made inuycyble the manna that was gyuen from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys body, &amp; the water powred out of the rocke his blode The which Dauid perceyuinge dyd proteſt in the holy gooſt, ſayenge: man hath eaten the breade of angels. It ware a fond thynge to ſuppoſe that thys corporall manna geuen to oure fathers, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the heuenly hooſt of angels, or that they do eate any ſuche meate which be rether fedde wyth the dayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes of goddes worde The pſalmyſt declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th playne or the holye gooſt rather ſpeaketh in the pſalmyſte, both what our fathers receyued in that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na, and what the faythfull ought to beleue in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; blode of chriſt: in the both truly chriſt is ſignifyed, whych is not only the meate of angels, but alſo fedeth the ſoules of the faytfull. And neyther of theſe happen in corporall taſt or feadyng, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of the ſpirituall worde, The eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſte teachet that Ieſus chriſte before he ſuffred, toke breade gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes &amp; diſtributed it to his apoſtles, ſayeng: thys is my body whych ſhalbe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you, do this in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce. Lykewyſe he toke the cup after he had ſupt, ſayeng: thys is the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloude, which ſhalbe ſhed for you. We ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt dyd worke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſtery of his body &amp; blode before he ſuffered. We
<pb facs="tcp:16106:6"/>dought not but euery faythfyll man beleueth that the breade was made the bodye of chriſte whych he gaue to hys diſciples, ſayeng: thys is my body that is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you. And alſo that the cuppe dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyne the blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of chriſt, whereof he ſayeth, thys cuppe is the newe teſtament in my bloude that ſhalbe ſhedde for you. Therfore as he coulde turne the ſubſtance of breade and the creature of wyne into hys proper body befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he dyed So coulde he in the deſerte, turne the man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na and the water of the rocke into hys fleſſhe &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not wythſtandinge that his fleſhe was hanged on the croſſe for vs. And hys bloude ſhed for vs longe af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter heare alſo we ought to conſyder what is ment by thes wordes, excepts you ſhall eate the fleſſhe of the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; drynke hys bloude, you ſhall not haue lyfe in you. He ſayde not that hys fleſſhe whych han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the croſſe ſhulde be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in pecys &amp; eaten of the Apoſtles, nor that hys blode whych he ſhedde for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world ſholde be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys diſciples to drinke, for it ware a wycked thing, yf hys fleſhe ſhuld be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or his bloud dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the infydelles toke it. Therfore, he ſayd to his diſciples takyng the wordes of chriſt not vnfaythfully, yt ſcarcely perceyuing how the ſame was to be vnderſtand, thes doughtes offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Therfore yf you ſhall ſe the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſcendynge thether where as he was before As though he ſhulde ſaye, you maye not thynke my fleſhe to be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of you corporally, or my bloude to be drouken of you corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, neyther that my flſhe ſhalbe deuyded into pecys for aſmuch as after my reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhal ſe me affen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth the fulnes of my holy body &amp; blode the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhal wel perceyue that my fleſhe is not to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thos that beleue as the infydels thynke, but that the bread &amp; the wyne chaunged by a myſterye into the ſubſtance of my body &amp; bloude is to be receyued of the
<pb facs="tcp:16106:7"/>faythfull, he ſayeth alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. The ſperite is he that quickeneth the fleſh profyteth nothing after eny ſuch ſorte as the vnfaythfull vnderſtande, other wyſe it gyueth lyfe as the faythfull take it by a myſterye. And therfore he ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſperite is he that quickeneth So in this myſterye of the body &amp; bloude of Chriſte, here is a ſpirituall operacion geuyng lyfe, wyth u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the whych operacion the myſteryes be vnprofyatable for well maye they fede the bodye: but the ſoule they cannot Here ſpringeth a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e whych propoſed ſome ſaye that thos thynges be done in verite, &amp; not in myſterye wherin they ſhewe them ſelues playn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lye to repungue agaynſt the wrytynges of the holye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Saynte Auſten the doctour of the churche in the thyrde of hys boke de doctrina chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ana wryteth thus Excepte you eate (ſayeth our ſauyour) the fleſhe of the ſonne of man &amp; drynke hys bloude, you ſhal ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue no lyfe in you, He ſemyth to commaund a wycked thyng, therfore it is a fygure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyng vs to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municators of hys paſſion, ſurelye alſo &amp; profytable to peruerte in our memories, that his fleſhe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd &amp; crucifyed for our ſakes Thus ſaynt Auſten af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the myſterye of the body and bloud of chriſt to be celebrate of the faythfull vnder a fygure, for he ſayeth it is no poynte of religion but rather of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te to take hys fleſſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hys bloud carnally, as they did whych vnderſtode not chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wordes ſpyry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye but carnallye &amp; wente back therfore and departed from hym. Among many thynges in hys Epyſtell to bonyeface he wryteth thus. Truelye we vſe to ſaye of tymes when Eſter draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th nere that tomorowe or nexte daye ſhalbe the paſſyon of the Lorde: not wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng he ſuffered hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many yeres befor. Ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther dyd he ſuffre but ons Alſo on Eaſter day, we cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably ſaye this daye the Lorde hath ryſen And it manye yeares hath paſſyed in dede ſyns he roſe.
<pb facs="tcp:16106:7"/>for ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this we ſhuld be reported as ſhameful lyers ſauing that we do name thys after the ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litude of the dayes them ſelues, wherin the thinges were done So we may ſay thys is the daye, though it be not the day it ſelfe in dede. But by the reuelacyon of tyme ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vnto it. And ſo we ſay the thynge is done this day for the celebracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whych is not done thys day in dede, but was done a great whyle before was not chriſt once offred in him ſelfe? And yet in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he is offred to the faythful people, not only euery Eaſter, but euery day, nether is he founde a lyer that anſwereth to a man (aſkyng the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that he is offered For yf the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had not a certayne ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litude of thoſe thinges wherof they be ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes they were no ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes at all, for the lykenes many tymes the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes take the names of the thynges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. Therfore lyke as after a ſorte the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body of chriſt, is the body of chriſt, &amp; the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of chriſt, is the bloud of chriſt. So the ſacramet of fayth is fayth. Thus we perceyue that ſaint Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affyrmeth the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be one thyng, &amp; the thynge it ſelfe to be another thynge, wherof the ſacramente is the bodye in the whyth chriſt ſuffered, &amp; the blode whych flowed from his ſyde are the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but the myſteries of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayeth he) be the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the body and bloude of chriſt, which ar ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of chryſtes paſſyon. Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at euery paſcall ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nite, but euery day in the yere. And although there is but one body of the lord in the whych he ſuffered: &amp; but one bloud that was ſhed for the helthe of the worlde, yet the ſacramentes of theſe thynges haue taken there names, ſo that we cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and bloude of chriſte for the ſimilitudes of the thinges which they ſignifye. So they be called after the ſame maner as the paſcall feaſte and the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb facs="tcp:16106:8"/>are whyche verelye be celebrated, &amp; yet chryſte ſuffred but once in hym ſelfe, and roſe agayne, nether can thoſe dayes be reuoked for they are paſte. 
The dayes in the whych the memorie of the lordes paſſion &amp; reſurrection be celebrated are named the ſelfe ſame dayes in whych chryſt ſuffered and roſe, becauſe they haue a ſymilitude of the verye ſame dayes in dede. Wherfore we ſay, thys day, tomorowe or nexte daye is the reſurrection of the lorde. Not withſtandinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the day in the whiche be roſe in dede, is many yeares paſt. Do we ſaye that the lorde is offered, whan the ſacrament of hys body and bloude be celebrated. Where as he was offered but ones in hym ſelfe for the health of the worlde. As the apoſtles ſayeth, chriſt ſuffred ones for you, leauynge an example that you myght folow hys foteſteppes. He doth not ſaye that he ſuffereth euery daye, whych he dyd once. He hath lefte vs an example whych is dayly preſented to thoſe whych beleue in the myſtery of the bodye &amp; bloude of chriſt. That whoſoeuer ſhall come to it, maye knowe that he ought to be aſſocyate to hys paſſions, whoſe Image he loketh for in the holy myſteries accordinge to the ſayeng of the wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou arte come to the table of a greate man, attende deligently what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are ſet before the, knowynge that thou thy ſelfe muſt prepare lyke thynges. To come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table of a great man is to be partaker of the lordes ſouper The conſyderation of the thynges ſet before the is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellygence of the body &amp; bloude of chriſt. Wherfore whoſoeuer is partaker, let hym know that he ought to prepare lyke thynges. That is to ſay, he muſte imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate chriſt in dyenge wyth hym, the remembraunce of whoſe death he acknowledgeth, not onely in beleuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, but alſo in taſtynge.</p>
               <p>Furthermore ſaynt Paule ſayeth to the Ebrews: yt
<pb facs="tcp:16106:8"/>was meete that we ſhuld haue ſuch a byſhop. That is to ſaye, holy Innocent, wythout ſpotte ſegregate from ſynners, and hygher then the heauens, whyche ſhall not nede as the other byſhoppes, dayly to offer for hys owne ſynnes, and after for the ſynnes of the people. Thys oure Lorde Ieſus chriſte hath done in offerynge hym ſelfe once, and that whych he dyd once, he doth now dayly freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, once he offered him ſelfe for the ſynnes of the people, the ſame oblacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is dayly celebrate among the faythfull: but it in a miſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, for that whych chriſt hath once fulfylled in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge hym ſelfe is dayly done in the church in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of hys paſſion by the celebracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes. Neyther it is falſly ſayd, that the Lord is of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered, or that he ſuffereth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſteries, for aſmuch as they haue the ſymilitude of hys death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof they be repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Wherfore the myſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries be named the body and bloude of chriſt, becauſe they take the appellation of thinges wherof they be ſacramentes.</p>
               <p>SAynt Yſodore in hye boke wherin he entreteth of the true ſygnificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of words, ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifyce is an holy thynge done, or the doynge of an holy thynge, for by a myſtical prayer it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecrate in the remembraunce of the Lordes paſſion. Therfore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to call it the body and bloude of chriſt, And though it be made of the frutes of the earth, it is ſanctifyed and made a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the inuyſible working of the holy ghoſt. The grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do call thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euchariſtia, that is by interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. good grace, and what is better then the bodye and bloude of chriſt The bread and the wyne truely are comparyd to the body and blond of chriſt. Becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that as the vyſyble ſubſtance of bread and wyne
<pb facs="tcp:16106:9"/>doth noryſh and inebriate the externe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of god (which is the lyuely bread) by hys pertici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth recreate the myndes of the faythful. And this catholike teacheth that the ſame myſtery of the Lordes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſte be done for vs in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the ſame. Thus he declareth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was once done, &amp; that the memorie of it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the ſolemnicies of holy thinges. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the breade whyche is made of the frutes of the ground is tranſpoſyd whyles he is ſanctifyed into the bodye of chriſt. And the wyne that floweth oute of the grape by the ſanctificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the godly myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, is made the bloude of chriſt, not viſybly: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the mynde of thys preſent doctor through the ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration of the holy gooſt, wherfore they ar called the body and bloude of Chriſt and ſo taken, not bycau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe they do ſo appere externely: but for that they ar ſo made by the worke of the holy gooſte, and for that they be an other thyng by the inuyſyble power, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vyſyble they ſeme to be. He maketh a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les he ſayeth. The bread and the wyne be comparyd to the body and bloud of chriſt. Bycauſe that as the ſubſtaunce of the viſyble bread wyne doth inebriate and noryſh the externe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo the word of god which is the lyuely bread (by the participacion of it) dothe refreſhe &amp; recreate the myndes of the faythful. Here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he confeſſeth very playnly, that what externe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſoeuer we receyue, it is accommodate to the refec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the body: but the worde of god whych is the inuiſible bread beyng in the ſacrament inuiſyble, by thys participacion in quyckening the myndes of the faythfull feadeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo the ſame doctor ſayeth: a ſacrament is in ſome celebracion, when the thyng is ſo done that it maye he vnderſtonde to ſygnyfye ſome what whych is to be taken wyth holynes, by
<pb facs="tcp:16106:9"/>this he declareth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eny ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in holy thynges con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth ſome ſecret &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teaching which appereth viſible &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych we ought to perceyue inuyſyble be dyuers. Afterwarde he declareth what ſacramentes are to be celebreate amonge the faythfull, that is the ſacrament of baptyſme and of the bodye and bloude of Chriſte whych are called ſacramentes for that a deuyne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue doth ſecretely worke the helthe receyued in them vnder the couer of corporall thynges. Wherfore they be called ſacramentes, of ſecret or holye vertue. He ſayeth alſo that a myſtery by his ſygnifycacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is that whych hath an hyd, and ſecrete diſpoſycion. Here in we be taught that the bodye and bloude of chriſte be called myſteries, bycauſe they haue an hydde and and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete diſpoſicion. That is to ſaye, a ſacramente hath one thynge whych he doth externely and playnely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and on other thynge whych worketh inuyſyble. They be called ſacramentes, for that a godlye vertue doth ſecretely diſpoſe the helthe of them whych fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully take them vnder the couer of corporall thynges Hether to haue we declared that the bodye and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Chriſt whych are receyued in the church by the mouthes of the faythfull be fygures after the vyſyble forme, but after the inuiſible ſubſtance that is to ſaye through the power of goddes worde they be the very bodye and bloude of chriſte, Therfore by the viſible creatures they feade and noryſhe the bodye, but by the vertue of the more excellente ſubſtaunce they feade and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the mynde of the faythfull.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:16106:10"/>
               <head>¶ The ſeconde queſtion foloweth.</head>
               <p>NOw let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder the ſeconde queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was borne of marie, that ſufferd dyed was buryed &amp; ſytteth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght hand of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dayly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued in the church by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthes of the faythful in the myſterie of the ſacrament or no. &amp;c. Saynte Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros in the fyrſt boke of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſayeth Truly it is a meruelous th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng that god dyd rayne ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our fathers, and that they ware dayly fed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wyth heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly noryſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, Wherfore it is ſayd man hath eaten the breade of angels. But yf al they whych eate bread in the deſerte are dead. Thys mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whych thou receyueſte. Thys lyuely breade whych hath diſcendyd from heauen doth myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of euerlaſtinge lyfe. And who ſo eateth of thys bread ſhall neuer dye for it is the body of chriſt Se how thys doctor calleth the body of chriſt meate which the faythfull receyue in the church. Thys brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſayeth he whych hath diſcendyd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth miniſter the ſubſtaunce of euerlaſtynge lyfe, not that whych is ſene corporally receyuyd, preſſed with teeth ſwalowed wyth throte, and ſent downe into the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, doth myniſter the ſubſtance of euerlaſtynge lyfe. For by thys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feadeth the fleſh whych ſhal dye. Ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther can it myniſter any incorrupcion. In thys reſpec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te trulye we can not ſaye who ſoeuer ſhall eate thys bread ſhall neuer dye, for that whych the body recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth is corruptible, &amp; cannot by any meane bryng to paſſe that the bodye maye lyue euer, for whatſoeuer is ſubiecte to corrupcion can gyue no eternyte, Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in that breade there is lyfe whych appereth not to oure corporall ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but that is loked vppon wyth the aſpects of oure fayth, that is the lyuely breade in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede
<pb facs="tcp:16106:10"/>that diſcended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of the whych it is truly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whoſoeuer eateth thys breade ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dye, whych is the body of chriſt. Alſo in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quences, where he ſpeaketh of the omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r vertue of chriſt, he ſayeth thus, the worde of chriſte, whyche coulde make of nothing that whych was not, is able to chaunge thos thynges whych be into that thynge whych they were not, for it is harder to gyue newe thynges, then to chaunge natures. Saynte ambroſe ſayeth in the myſterie of the body and bloud of chriſt there is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made marueloouſly, for it is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de by an incomprehenſyble maner, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaye here whych eſteme not the ſecrete vertue: but the whole whych appereth viſyble, how and in what poynt he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re happeneth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of the creatures, they be euen the ſame thynges after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecration, that they were before. For before the conſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cration they were breade and wyne, &amp; after they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere to remayne in the ſame kynde ſtyl. Therfore the mutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made internely by the power of the holy gooſt, whych only fayth loketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Which feadeth the ſoule and myniſtreth the ſubſtance of euerlaſting lyfe. He ſayeth alſo, why doeſt thou ſeke for the order of nature here in the body of chriſte, ſayenge he was bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of a virgyn beynge both god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyonde the courſe of nature. Here alſo ryſeth the hearer and affyrmeth the bodye of chriſt to be that whych is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and the bloude whyche is dronke Say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge that he ought not to enquyre how it is made: but to bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue that it is made: He appereth to thynke wel, but yf he conſyder delygently the nature of wordes, he ſhal pereceyue he ſayeth not the thynge which he beleueth. For yf he myghte ſaye I ſe the bodye and bloude of Chriſt he could not ſaye I beleue the body and blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of chriſt, to be there, Now for aſmuche as faythe
<pb facs="tcp:16106:11"/>loketh on the hole, whatſoeuer it be, and the eye of the fleſhe apprehendeth no thynge, he ſhall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that the bodye and bloude or chriſte be not in the forme but in vertue. Wherfore he ſayth that the order of nature is not to be loked for, but the power of Chriſt to be worſhypped whych doth create what ſoeuer he lyſte, and chaungeth that thynge whyche is create into ſome what that it was not before, at hys pleaſure,</p>
               <p>The ſame auctor ſayeth, that was the trewe and verye fleſhe whyche was crucyfyed and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed. Truly therfore of the ſame fleſſhe the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, the Lord ſayeth thys is my bodye. Howe dyligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; how wyſely hath he made a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he ſayeth touchyng the fleſhe whych was crucified and buryed. Thys is the true fleſhe of Chriſte, but tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge that whych is receyued in the ſacrament, he ſayeth, thys is the ſacramente of the true fleſhe, ſo deuydinge the ſacrament of the fleſhe, from the very fleſhe for aſmoche as he ſayde in the verye fleſhe whych he toke of the vyrgyne marye, he was crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and buryed.</p>
               <p>But he affyrmeth the myſterye whych is done in the churche to be the ſacramente of the verye fleſhe in the whyche Chriſte ſuffered, inſtructynge the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, that the fleſſhe in the whyche Chriſte ſuffred and was crucifyed and buryed, is not a myſterye, but the verye naturall fleſſhe. But thys fleſſhe whyche nowe conteyneth the ſymylytude of the verye fleſhe in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, is not fleſhe in kynde, nor in for me, but in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
               <p>For in kynde it is breade and in Sacramente the true bodye of Chriſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As the LORDE cryeth thys is my bodye. Alſo he ſayeth further, that the holye ghooſte hathe other wyſe expreſſed thys, ſayen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,
<pb facs="tcp:16106:11"/>What ſhall we eate, or what ſhall we drynke. Mat. v. Alſo by hys Prophete, ſayenge, Taſte and ſe for the LORDE is ſwete, bleſſed is that man whyche truſteth in hym.</p>
               <p>Do you thynke that thys breade taſted corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye? or thys wyne dronken corporally? can you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare howe ſwete the breade is? whatſoeuer ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth is corporall and declareth the bodye ſence. Shall we thynke to taſte the LORDE, is to feade anye corporall thynge? Therfore the ſpirituall taſte byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth vs to proue the ſauer, and in that breade and that drynke to opynyonate nothyng corporally, but to feale the hole ſpiritually, for the LORDE tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye is a ſperite. He ſayeth further in the Sacramente is Chriſte. For the bodye of Chriſte is there: but he doth not ſaye that the wyne or the breade is Chriſte, For yf he ſholde ſaye ſo (as God forbydde he ſholde) then he muſte pronounce the bodye of Chriſte to be corporall. And ſubiecte to mortalite for what ſoeuer is perceyued and taſted in that meate corporally is ſubiecte to corruption, he addeth thes wordes, (or it is the bodye of Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Therfore peraduenture a man wyll ſaye, lo he doth manyfeſtelye confeſſe the breade and the wyne to be the bodye of Chriſte. But take hede howe it is added, for it is no corporall meate but a ſpyrytuall meate. Therfore you ſhall not adhybit the ſence of the fleſſhe. For nothynge is perceyued here after that ſense.</p>
               <p>There is the bodye of Chriſte howe be it not corporall but ſpirituall. The bloude of Chriſte is the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, howe be it not corporall but ſpirituall. Therfore nothynge here is to be iudged corporally. Here is the bodye of Chriſte, but not corporally. Here is the blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of Chriſte but not corporally. He ſayeth further
<pb facs="tcp:16106:12"/>wherfore the apoſtel ſpeakynge of the figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſayeth our fathers haue eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ſpiritual meate, and dronken the ſame ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drinke, for the body of chriſt is a ſpirituall bodye the bodye of chriſte is the bodye of the deuyne ſpirite. For chriſt is a ſperite as we rede <bibl>lamentationu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> l 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</bibl>
                  <q>Spiritus ante facia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtram xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dominus.</q>
He hath taught vs moſte playnely howe we ought to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the myſterye of the bodye and bloude of chriſt what he ſayde, that our fathers dyd eate the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meate, and drynke the ſpirituall drinke, notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge that the manna whych they eate, and the water whych they dronke were corporall thynges, he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dyth of the myſteryes which is now celebrate in the churche, defynynge how it is the bodye of chriſte. The bodye of god ſayeth he, is a ſpirituall body. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo god is chriſte, and the bodye whych he toke of the virgyn marye, in the whych he ſuffered, in the whych he was buryed, in the which he roſe agayne was the very and the trew bodye, and the ſame remayned vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble and palpable, but the body whych is called the myſterye of god is not corporall, but ſpirituall, it is not viſyble nor palpable. To this doth ſaynte ambro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe adioyne ſayenge, the bodye of Chriſte is the bodye of the deuyne ſperite, and a deuyne ſperite is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall corruptyble ne palpable, but this body whych is celebrate in the church through hys vyſyble vynde is corruptable and palpable. Howe then is it calied the body of the deuyne ſpirite? Verely in the reſpecte that it is ſpirituall. That is to ſaye inuiſyble and inpalpable, and therfore incorruptable, he ſayeth becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe Chriſt is a ſpirite, as we rede Spiritus ante facia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtus dominus. He ſheweth manyfeſtlye by what mean the bodye of Chriſte is hadde, that is to ſaye by the reaſon that the ſperite of Chriſte is in it,
<pb facs="tcp:16106:12"/>that is the power of goddes worde, whych doth not only feade the ſoule but alſo purgeth it. Wherfore the auctor conſequentely ſayeth. Thys meate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth our hartes, and thys drinke maketh gladde the harte of man as the prophete hath mencyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, is it not corporall meate thynke you whyche confyrmeth the harte of man or corporall drynke whych exhilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate mans harte? but that he myghte ſhewe: what meat or what drynke he ſpeaketh of, (he hath added thys meate, and this drinke, what meat doth he mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne? or what drynke? Verely the bloude of Chriſt, the body of the deuyne ſperite. And to ſpeake playnely, the ſperite of whom it is reade. Spiritus ante faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am noſtram xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, dominus In all thys thynges it is euident, that we muſte take nothynge in thys mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or thys drynke corporally: but that the hole muſte be attendyd ſpiritually. For the ſoule wyth in thys place is ſygnyfyed by the harte of man, is not fedde wyth corporall meate or corporal drynke: but nuryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed it is and made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge wyth the worde of God. Which thing this ſame doctor affyrmeth more pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye in the fyrſt boke of the ſacraments, ſayenge: The bread whych goeth into our bodyes, is not the bread whyche mynyſtreth ſubſtaunce to oure ſoules, but the breade of euerlaſtynge lyfe. And the leſſon follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng declareth moſte playnely, that ſaynte Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dyd not meane here the rome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread but the breade of the bodye of Chriſte. For he doth ſpeake of the daylye breade whych the faythfull deſyreth to be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them. And therefore he addyth, yf it be daylye breade, why doeſte thou take it but ons in the yere? as the grecyans were wount in the eſter. Take ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that whych maye daylye profytt the and lyue ſo that thou mayeſt deſyre to take it daylye. Therfore it is
<pb facs="tcp:16106:13"/>vertue: And it is cleane another thyng whych is ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> externly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is beleued in the myſterie Moreouer the fleſſhe of chriſte that was crucifyed, did not ſhewe one thyng out wardly, and was an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng inwardely, for it was the verye fleſſhe of man, and a body conſyſtynge in the kynde of a very body. We muſt alſo conſydre, that in the breade, not only the body of chriſt is fygured, but alſo the body of the beleuyng people. For as the bread is made of many graynes of wheate, ſo the bodye of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, is augemented with manye of thoſe that beleue, by the word of chryſte. Wherfore as in the mysterye the breade is taken for the body of chryſte, ſo lykewyſe the membres of the beleuinge people in chryſt, be intinuate in the ſame myſterye. And as the breade is the bodye of the faythfull men, not corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally but ſpiritually So we muſt neceſſarely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that the ſame is the body of chriſt, not corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, but ſpiritually Lykewyſe in the wyne whyche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s called the bloude of chriſt, water is myxte, and the one is permytted wythout the other. For as the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple can not be wythout Chriſte, nor chriſte wythout the people: ſo the head cannot be wythout the bodye nor the bodye wythout the heade. The water in thys ſacrament, beareth the Image of the people. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yf that the wyne ſanctifyed by the offyce of the mynister, were corporally chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into the blode of Chriſt: then the water whych is myxte wyth it, ſhulde neceſſarely be chaunged corporally into the blode of he faythfull people. For where as is one ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yon, there is conſequently one operacion: and wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as is lyke reaſon, there is lyke myſterye. But we ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat nothynge is chaunged in the water corporally: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herfore it foloweth, that nothynge is chaunged cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porally in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: what ſoeuer is ſignifyed in the
<pb facs="tcp:16106:13"/>water of the people, is taken ſpiritually: therfore we muſt nedis take ſpiritually, whatſoeuer is intinuate in the wyne of the body of chryſt. Moreouer thinges which do dyffer, be not all one. The bodye of chriſte that dyed, roſe agayne, and was immortal, dyeth no more, death ſhall no more beare rule ouer it, for it is eternall and ſhall ſuffre no more. But that whych is celebrate in the churche is temporal, not eternal, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, not incorruptible, in the way, not in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey Therfore they dyffer and be not all one, and yf they be not all one how is it called the body of chriſt and the verye blode? For yf it be the verye bodye of chriſt, and be called the ſame: Truly becauſe it is the body of chriſte, it is the body of chriſte in verite, that is to ſay. Yf it be the very body of chriſt, then it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of chriſt incorruptyble and inpaſſyble, and by that eternall. Therfore by thys reaſon, the bodye of chriſt whych is celebrate in the churche, muſt neades be incorruptible, and eternall: but we can not denye that thyng to be corruptible, whych is deuyded in pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, broken with our tethe, and goeth into the belye: but that is one thyng whych is done externly, &amp; that an other whych is beleued by fayth, whatſoeuer the ſences attayne vnto, is corruptible, and that whych fayth beleueth is incorruptible, Therfore that which appereth outwardly, is not the thynge it ſelf, but an Image of the thynge, but that whych is perceyued &amp; underſtande in the mynde, is the very thynge. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saynt Auſten ſpeakynge of the body and blode of chriſt in the expoſicyon of the goſpell of S. Ihon ſayet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus. Moyſes dyd eate manna, Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd eat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dyd eate, and many moo dyd eate whyche pleaſed god, &amp; they dyed not Why? Uerelye becauſe they vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtode the viſyble meate ſpirituallye, they fylled them ſelues ſpirituallye, We alſo do receyue
<pb facs="tcp:16106:14"/>nowe the viſible meate, yet the ſacrament is one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and the vertue of the ſacrament an other, he ſayeth alſo. This is the breade whiche diſcended from heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manna dyd ſignifye this breade, the altare of god dyd ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fye this breade, theſe ware ſacramentes, &amp; dyuers in theyr fygures, yet in the thynge whiche is ſignifyed, they were lyke, Here the apoſtle Paule. I wolde not haue you ignoraunte, o brethren (ſayeth he) that our fathers were vnder a cloude, and al they paſſed ouer the ſee, and all were baptyſed in moyſes in the cloude, and in the ſee, and all they dyd eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, &amp; all they dyd drynke the ſame ſpirituall drynke, therfore they dyd eate the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall meate that we do, for there corporall meate was an other thynge, they dyd eate manna, we eate an other thynge, yet theyr ſpirituall meate was all one with oures, he addith, and all they dyd drynke on ſpirituall drynke. In the viſible kynde our drynke &amp; they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is were dyuers: yet in the ſpirituall vertue, they dyd both ſignifye one thynge. How dyd they drynke the ſame? They dronke (ſayeth he) of the ſpirituall ſtone folowynge them, and the ſtone truly was chriſt from whence they had the breade, from whence they had the drynke: the ſtone was chryſte in a fygure, the very chryſt is in fleſhe and blode. Further this is the breade diſcendynge from heuen, that yf any man eate of it he ſhall lyue for euer: but it is that whiche pertei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth to the vertue of the ſacrament, and not the viſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſacrament it ſelfe. And he ſhall lyue whiche eateth within &amp; not he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth withoute, whiche eatethe in his harte, &amp; not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> braketh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his touthe. He ſayeth alſo repetynge the wordes of out ſauyour: this doth offend you, becauſe I ſay, I gyue my fleſh to be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of you, &amp; my blode to be dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore yf you ſhal ſe: he ſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng where he was fyrſt. What meaneth this? Here he diſſolued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which moued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:16106:14"/>Here he diſcloſed wherfore they were offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. They thought that he wold haue ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his body among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> But he ſayde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold aſcend hole into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſe the ſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng where he was fyrſt: tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly then ye ſhall ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll not beſtowe his body ſo as ye ſantifye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll. Verely ye ſhall vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his grace is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed by morſels. Alſo he ſayth hym ſelf. The ſpirite is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> quyckeneth: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyteth nothyng. The wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you (ſayeth chriſt) be ſpirite &amp; lyfe: that is to ſay, they are ſpiritually to be vnderſtande. Thou haſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſpiritually: they be ſpirite &amp; lyfe vnto the. Thou haſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d carnally? they be ſpirite &amp; lyfe: but not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Thus we are taught, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auctorite of this doctor, in treatynge of the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of his body &amp; bloude: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe wordes of chriſte are to be vnderſtande ſpiritually, &amp; not carnally. As he ſayeth, the wordes which I ſpoke to you be ſpirit &amp; lyfe: he meaneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpoke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the eating of his fleſh, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drinke of his blod: wher with the apoſtles were offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Therfore leſt they ſhuld be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſtyl, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euyne mayſter calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh to the ſpirite: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corporall viſyon to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſible intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. We ſe therfore, after what maner the meate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord: &amp; the drink of his blod be his very body &amp; his very blod. Verely i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſpect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be ſpirite &amp; lyfe: thinges that be al one be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended in one definicion: It is ſayd of the very body of chriſt, that he is very god &amp; very man: god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was borne of the father before the begynninge: man that was borne in the later dayes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgyn mary. Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge that theſe thynges cannot be ſayd of the body of chriſte whych is in the churche by a myſterye: it is knowen to be the body of chriſt, but after a certayn maner: thys maner is in fygure, and in Image, that the verite and the thynge it, ſelfe maye be perceaued
<pb facs="tcp:16106:15"/>in the prayers whyche are ſayde after the myſterye, of the body &amp; bloude of chriſt, to the whyche the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay amen. Thus it is pronunced, with the voyce of the preiſt: we takyng the pledge of euerlaſting lyfe deſyre moſt humbly, that we may receyue with mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt participacion, that thynge whych we touche in the Image of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thus they be the pledge and the Image of an other thyng, that is to ſay, they reſpecte an other thyng and not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues A pledge is of that thynge, for the whych it is geuen. An Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge is an Image, of that thynge whoſe ſymilitude it ſheweth Theſe do ſygnifye the thinges wherof th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be, but they do not manifeſtly ſhew them, ſaying: it is ſo, it appereth that this body a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d bloude, are the pledge and the Image of the thynge to come: that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge it ſelfe, whych is now ſhewed by a ſymilitude may here after be reueled manyfeſtly. And yf they ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifye that thyng now which here after ſhal be many<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſte: doutles it is one thynge whych is done nowe, and an other that ſhalbe manifeſte in tyme to come. Wherfore that whych is celebrated of the church, is the bodye and bloude of chriſt: but it is a pledge, and as an Image, the verye bodye ſhal be ſene: whan no Image and pledge ſhall appere, but the verite of the thynge it ſelfe. Thys alſo is another prayer whyche is vſed about the ſacramente, Make perfyte in vs good lord we beſeche the that that thyng whych the ſacrament dothe conteyne, that we maye take thoſe thynges in verite, whych at thys tyme we take in fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure He ſayeth that theſe thynges be done in fygure and not in verite. That is by a ſymilitude, &amp; not by the manifeſtacyon of the thynge it ſelfe. The fygure and the verite do dyffer betwene them ſelues. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the body and bloud that be now celebrate in the churche, do dyffer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body and thy bloude why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:16106:15"/>ar now knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be glorifyed, by the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, thys body is the pledge, &amp; the figure the other is the verye natural body. Thys we celebrate vnto ſuch tyme as we may come to the other: and after that we ſhall come to it, the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall body ſhalbe remoued nowe we ſe, that thes too bodyes differ aſmuche the one, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other: as the pledge doth from the thynge for whych it is left, and as the ymage differeth from the thynge, wherfore it is the ymage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and as the fygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re differeth from the verite, thus it is playne, that the myſterye of the body &amp; bloude of chriſt, whych is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the faythful: in the churche: differeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayde body, that was borne of marye the virgyn, that ſuffered &amp; was buryed, that roſe agayne, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſytteth on the ryght hande of the father. For thys whych is celebrate in the way muſte be ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vnderſtande, for fayth beleueth that thynge whych he ſeeth not, &amp; that fedeth the ſoule ſpiritually, maketh glad the harte, gyueth euerlaſtynge lyfe, &amp; incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whyles no hede is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the thyng, that fedeth the body, that is preſſed wyth the teeth, that is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in pecys: but that thynge, whych is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in fayth ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, but that body in the whych chriſt ſuffered, &amp; roſe agayne, is hys proper bodye take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the virgyne marye, palpable, &amp; viſyble: ye: after hys reſurrection he ſayth to his diſciples. Why be you troubled, &amp; why do fantiſes occupie youre hartes? loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my fete and my hande for I am he, grope and ſee, for a ſpryte hath no fleſhe, nor bones as ye ſe that I haue. Let vs alſo here what ſaynte fulgencius ſayeth in hys boke of fayth, beleue ſtedfaſtly &amp; doute not, but the onelye beggotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne of god, the worde was made fleſhe, &amp; that he offered hym ſelfe for vs, as a ſacrifice to god, in the order of ſwetnes: vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth the father &amp; the holy goſt, the patriarkes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes, the prieſts
<pb facs="tcp:16106:16"/>of the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, dyd ſacrifice beaſtes, &amp; vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth the father &amp; the holye ghoſt, wyth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath lyke deuynite: the holy vnyuerſal church through out all the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſeaſeth not in fayth, &amp; charite, nowe to offer the ſacrafice of breade &amp; wyne. In thos fleſhely ſacrifyces, was the ſignificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſhe of chriſt, whych he offered for our ſynnes: &amp; a ſignificacion of the bloude that he ſhede, for the remiſſion of our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes but in ſacrifice of breade &amp; wyne, is the action of thankes, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſhe of chriſt, that he offered for vs &amp; of the bloude that he ſhedde for vs Wherof of Saynte Paule ſpeaketh in the actes of the apoſtles ſayenge: take hede to you &amp; youre vniuerſall flocke, in the whyche the holye gooſte hath made you byſhopes, to gouerne the church of god, that he hath acquyred wyth hys bloude, 


therfore in the former ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fyces, it was ſygnifyed figuratyuely what ſhoulde be gyuen vs, &amp; in thys it is euydently ſhewed, what is gyuen vs already, for aſmuche as he ſayeth, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former ſacrifyces, it was ſygnifyed what ſhold be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, &amp; in thys ſacrifice, we reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre what is gyuen vs already. He declareth, that as the ſacrifices of the olde lawe, was fygures of the thynge that was it to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: ſo thys ſacryfice is a figure of the thyng which is already paſt. By theſe wordes he hath moſte playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſhewed, how muche difference is betwene the body in whych chriſt ſuffered: &amp; the body whych is celebrate in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; death, for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye wherin he ſuffered, is the proper &amp; the verye body hauyng no myſterie nor fygure in hym. But thys is a myſtycall body, ſhewying one thynge externely by a fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gure, &amp; repreſentyng an other thynge internly through the intellec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fayth. Yt let vs adde an other teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money of ſaynte Auſten that ſhall both affyrme oure wordes, &amp; fynyſhe oure oracion. In the ſermone that
<pb facs="tcp:16106:16"/>he made to the people, touchyng the ſacrament of the alter, he ſayeth thus. The thynge whych you ſe in the alter of god, was ſene of you the laſt nyght, but what it is, or what it meaneth, or of how<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great a thyne it conteyneth the ſacrament ye haue not it hearde The thyng whych you ſe is bread &amp; wyne, &amp; that your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s do argue: but as your fayth requyreth to be inſtructe the bread is the body of chriſt, &amp; the wyne hys bloude it is quyckely ſayed, that fayth perauenture is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: but fayth doughtles, neadeth inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Eſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi. ſayeth. Except ye beleue, ye ſhal not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore you maye ſaye vnto me, ſyr ye haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs to beleue: now expounde to vs, howe we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, ſuche a cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye ryſe in ſome mans mynde. Ye knowe that our Lord Ieſus toke hys fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe of the virgyn marye, that he beyng an infante dyd ſocke, &amp; was noryſhed, &amp; growed to a mans age, and brought to perſecution of the Iewes, ſuffered, &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a croſſe was kylled, &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, was buryed and roſe agayne the thyrde daye, and at hys pleaſure aſcendyd vnto heauen, and carryed hys body thether from whence he ſhall come to iudge the quycke, and deade, and there is he nowe ſyttyng of the ryght han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of the father, how therfore is the breade hys bodye and the wyne hys bloude? thes good brethren be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſacraments, bycauſe that one thynge is  ſene in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and an other vnderſtande, that whych is ſene, hath a corporall forme, &amp; that whych is not ſene hath a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall frute. In thes wordes, thy worſhypfull auctor inſtructyng vs, what we ought to thynke of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bodye of the Lord, that was borne of marye, and ſytteth nowe on the ryght hande of the father, in the whych he ſhall come to iudge the quycke &amp; the deade. Alſo what we ought to thynke of the body ſet on the alter, wherof the people be partakers, the very bodye
<pb facs="tcp:16106:17"/>is hole, and not deuyded wyth any ſectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neyther co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered wyth any fygures: but thys bodye ſette on the table of the Lorde is a fygure, becauſe it is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the externe thynge whyche is ſene, hath a corporall forme that feadeth the body: but the interne thyng whych is vnderſtande, hath a ſpirituall fruite that quyckeneth the ſoule, and he wyllynge to ſpeake more playnly and manyfeſtly of the myſticall bodye, ſayeth thus, yf you wyll vnderſtande the body of the Lord, heare the Apoſtell ſayenge you be the bodye of chriſte And the membres. Therfore yf ye be the bodye of chriſte, and the membres of chriſt, your myſterye is conteyned in the Lordes ſouper, you take the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the lord, and vnto that thyng whych you your ſelues be, you anſwre ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in anſwryng, you ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcrybe, therefore thou heareſt the body of chriſt &amp; thou anſwreſt amen. Be thou a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of the body of chriſt that that the amen may be true. and wherin, in breade we wyll ſpeake nothynge or oure owne heades, but heare the Apoſtell. We beynge manye (ſayeth he) are one breade, and one bodye, &amp;c. Therfore Sayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Auguſtyne hath taught vs, that as the bodye of Chriſte is ſygnyfyed in the breade whyche is on the alter, ſo is the body of the people that receyueth it, Alſo he hath euidently ſhewed, that the proper bodye of chryſte, is that body in the which he was borne of the virgyn marye, in the which he ſucked in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he ſuffred, in the whiche he dyed, and was buried in the whiche he roſe and aſcended into heauen, in the whiche he ſytteth of the ryght hand of the father and in the whiche he ſhall come agayne to iudgemet. But this whiche is ſet on the lordes table, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the myſterye of the very body: euen as it dothe of the myſterye of the beleuyng people. For the appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayeth. We beynge maney, are one breade and one bodye.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16106:17"/>
               <p>YOURE wyſdome (moſt excellente prynce) may perceyue, that I haue prouyd by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of holy ſcryptures, and of the holy fathers: that the breade whiche is called the body of chryſte, and the cup called his blode, is a fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure becauſe it is a myſterye. And that there is no ſmall dyfference, betwene the myſtycall bodye, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye that ſuffered, was buryed and roſe agayne. For this whiche ſuffered, is the proper body of oure ſauyour. Neyther in it is any fygure, or ſignifycaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but the manifeſtacyon of the thying it ſelfe is kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen. And the viſyon of it ſhulde be deſyred of the faythfull. For after we ſhall ſe it, youre deſyre ſhalbe accomplyſhed, for he and the father be all one, &amp; not in the reſpecte of our ſauyours bodye: but in the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte of the fulnes of deuinite, that dwellethe in the man chryſte, But in this myſtycall body is a fygure, not onely of the proper body of chryſt: but alſo of the people beleuyng in chriſt. For doutles it beareth the fygure both of the body of chryſt that ſuffered &amp; roſe agayne, and of the people borne agayne by baptyſme and made alyue from the death of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Let vs adde alſo that the breade and the wyne, named the bodye and blode of chryſt: do repreſent the memorye of the lordes paſſyon &amp; death For he ſayeth in the goſpell. Do this in my remembraunce. the whiche paule ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth: ſayenge So oft as ye eate of this breade &amp; drynke of this wyne, you ſhall ſhewe the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde tyll he come. Thus we be taught both of chryſt and of paule, that the breade and the wyne ſet on the altare, are ſet for a fygure or a memory of the lordes deathe, that it maye putte vs in remembraunce in the tyme preſent, what hath bene done in tyme paſt, that we made myndfull of his paſſyon, may be made alſo partakers of the godly rewarde, by the which we ar delyuered from death. Knowynge that after we ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:16106:18"/>once come to the viſyon of chryſte, we ſhall haue no nide of ſuche inſtrumentes, by the whiche we are put in remembraunce what chryſt hath ſuffered for vs. For we lokynge on hym face to face. ſhall not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhed by an externe admonicion of temporall thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: but by the contemplacyon of the truth it ſelfe. Yet we may gyue thankes to the auctor of our helth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t you ſhall not thinke for all this, that the body and blode of the lorde is not receyued of the faythfull in the myſterye of the ſacrament ſayenge that fayth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth not the thyng loked vppon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oure eyes, but that whiche is beleued. For the meate is ſpirituall, &amp; the drynke is ſpirituall, feadyng the ſoule ſpiritually and gyueth the lyfe of euerlaſtyng ſecrete: as our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour ſayeth The ſpirite is he that quyckeneth, the fleſſhe profyteth nothynge. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>les I haue indeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to obey the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of your excellencye. I a man of ſmall importancye, haue preſumed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pute of no ſmall thynges: yt not folowynge the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptyon of myne owne eſtimacyon or Iudgement But the auctoritie of the olde fathers, yf it happen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you approue theſe thynges as catholyke, it muſte be imputed to be merytes of our fayth, which was not aſhamed (the glorye of your regall magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce layed awaye for a tyme) to aſke a reſponce of the truth, of a pore man: but yf they pleaſe you not: let it be imputed to my folyſhnes it coulde not with efficacye explicate that thynge whiche you deſyred.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London in ſaynt Andrewes paryſhe in the waredropt, by Thomas Raynalde, and Anthony Kyngſtone.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16106:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
